Over the last year, MCP has really
become the go-to way for us to connect
our agents to our tools and data. But as
the protocol has gained popularity, it's
also become more and more obvious that
we have a major flaw with the protocol.
It is all about token consumption and
context rot, which are very much hot
topics right now. And Enthropic admitted
to this problem themselves, and they
literally built the protocol. So they
published this blog post recently
covering the main issue with MCP and
then their proposed solution to build
more efficient agents. That's what I
want to cover with you today in a very
practical way. So this video is going to
be a quick breakdown. I'm going to do it
very clearly for you. I want to cover
the problem we have with MCP with a full
example. Then we'll get into the
proposed solution. And I really think
that this is powerful stuff. And then I
know I'm being a little cheeky here
hiding this, but I want to cover the
final question. Is this the end of MCP
as we know it? The problem with MCP
servers is that they are incredibly
token inefficient and rigid. And
starting with the token inefficiency.
We've got a really nice diagram in the
anthropic article that I want to show
you quick. So every single tool
definition like the when and the Y for
the tool and the parameters and also
every single time we leverage the tool
both are going to fill our context
window. And so the more capabilities we
give our agent the more we are going to
bloat its context. And I've got a scary
example just to show you how quickly
this can get seriously out of hand. Cuz
right here I just have five very
standard MCP servers for AI coding. And
I've used these all a lot in the past,
but I would never, and I repeat, never
use them all in the same session with my
coding assistant because they each take
thousands of tokens just to describe
their capabilities to the AI agent. And
so these tokens are consumed at the
start of a conversation before we even
send our first message. And sure, modern
LLMs can handle this many tokens. But
just because the LLM can fit the tokens
doesn't mean it can handle it
gracefully. If we try to give this many
tools to our coding assistant right out
the gate, we're going to completely
overwhelm it and make it feel like we're
back in the stone age in 2022 running
our LLMs with GPT 3.5. And I've been
there. I've built agents back then. I
know how they could only handle a couple
of tools back then. And so, it's a lot
better now, but still, this is way too
much. And I'll prove to you that it
really is this bad. It's actually
bonkers. So, I'll go to my coding
assistant. I have all the same servers
connected. I'll go inside of Cloud Code
now. And then I'll run slashcontext to
show me how many tokens each of my
capabilities are taking. And wow, look
at this. We have a ton of tools here.
And overall, the MCP tools alone are
taking 97,000
tokens. That is 48% of the context
available for Claude Sonnet 4.5. And
even if you have an LLM that can take 1
million or 2 million tokens, this is
still just going to overwhelm with
capabilities. Okay, so that really
sucks. So the big question now is what
is the solution to this? What if I do
want all these capabilities given to my
agent at the exact same time? Well, what
we need to consider here is that we need
a way to give these capabilities to our
agent but only when they need to
leverage them. So we want more of a real
time discovery of the tools that are
available only loading in the content
and the context of the specific
capabilities when we want to use them.
So real time discovery or even creating
the capabilities on the fly. This is
code execution what Anthropic talks
about a lot in the article. We'll come
back to this in a second. So, first
think about this. Most MCP servers are
really just API wrappers for agents.
Like with my open source project archon,
just to give you an example, but a lot
of them work like this is we have all
these API endpoints to work with our
knowledge and our projects and our
tasks. And the code for the MCP server
itself, there's not actually much to it
because it's just an instruction set to
the agent. Here's a couple of functions
you can call to interact with our API
endpoints. And so the big question here,
let me zoom in on this. What if we just
allowed the agent to write the code
directly to interact with the Archon API
endpoints instead of having the MCP
server as the middleman that is loading
dozens of tools up front. So, not only
is this going to be way less tokens, but
it's also going to be a lot more
flexible because the agent gets to
decide how to interact with our API
instead of the MCP kind of forcing these
specific tools. Plus, the agent can save
the generated code to reuse later. So,
at first, the AI agent will generate the
scripts on demand and then maybe even
some instructions for how to use those
going forward. This is very related to
Claude skills that we'll talk about in a
second. And then when the agent needs to
leverage the capabilities later, it'll
load the instruction set plus the code
context and execute it. But it's only
going to be doing this when it needs to.
And so going back to our Enthropic
article, instead of all the MCP servers
being loaded right up front, we have
something kind of like this. It's a
folder that the agent can search through
in real time, discovering the
capabilities as it needs. Like maybe it
decides I should be doing something with
Google Drive now. And so it'll look at
this highle file to see the capabilities
there. And then maybe it'll load the
code specifically to get a document. So
it can look kind of something like this.
The sort of thing that would be loaded
right away with MCP, but now we're only
calling this once we want to do things
related to Google Drive. That's all just
based off of the user query. So the user
says something related to Google Drive.
Then we know we should load in these
capabilities. and having agents write
code to create their capabilities,
reusing code, like that all makes a lot
of sense because the LLMs these days are
really good at writing code and
developers should take advantage of this
to build agents that interact with MCP
servers or just API endpoints a lot more
efficiently. And when we think about
giving our agent the ability to execute
code and reuse code, it's not really
obvious how to do that. I mean, that's
one of the benefits of MCP. It's just
really easy to plug the MCP servers in
and instantly give these new
capabilities to our agents. But that is
where agent skills comes in. Enthropic
released this pretty recently and it
does embody the solution that we have to
the MCP problem because it gives us and
our AI agents the ability to generate
these scripts to do things like interact
with our API endpoints and generate
instructions for how to use these
scripts or create code on the fly. So
code execution at its finest. And this
is fantastic because the description for
this skill, this little bit of text
right here is the only thing that is
given to our AI agent at the start of a
conversation. So instead of thousands of
tokens defining tools and MCP
instructions, we just have a couple of
sentences here. And then when the agent
decides it wants to leverage the skill,
then we load the full instruction set
and the code that we want to execute.
And it doesn't even have to load all the
code, by the way. It can't just describe
like here are the functions you can call
and here's how you call them. And so
this is very very token efficient like 2
to 3% of the token usage compared to MCP
at the start of a conversation. So let
me know in the comments if you want me
to cover cla skills in a dedicated
video. There is so much to go over here
and it's so powerful and right now this
is just in the anthropic ecosystem. But
I think it's going to go way beyond that
very quickly here just like MCP did
because we can have dozens of skills
given to our agents at the same time
since it's a fraction of the token cost
upfront compared to MCP. And I don't
know if you noticed this yet, but the
skill that I'm using here as an example
is the one for Archon, my very own open-
source project. So, I took the Archon
MCP server, transformed it into a skill
to prove to myself and to you that we
have all the same functionality, and now
it is way more token efficient and
honestly flexible because the coding
assistant can now generate its own code
to interact with the Archon API. It is
fantastic. And so now we can pair this
with a ton of other different skills and
not worry about getting to that 90,000
tokens up front. Oh, and by the way,
I'll link to this in the description
with the Archon skill. I did a full
demonstration of this in the Dynamus
community and so I I proved it out like
this works as well as the MCP server and
it takes just a couple of hundred tokens
up front so you can try this out for
yourself if you want. So the last
question you're probably asking yourself
is is this the end of MCP? I mean the
picture that I laid out here is looking
pretty grim. But my short answer is no.
This is definitely not the end. And the
reason for this is MCP is actually
pretty great because what you see is
what you get. And what I mean by that is
when I build an MCP server, I define the
tools that people leverage when they're
using my service through MCP. And so I
have a lot more control and
predictability. So code execution is
flexible and very efficient like we saw,
but it's also risky and complicated.
There's a lot of security
considerations. We have to think about a
code sandbox environment that also makes
it more complicated. And so there is
really a big trade-off here between
control and flexibility. And so for MCP
servers, we get to control how the agent
leverages the tools because it's not
generating arbitrary code. More control
for things like credential setup, like
how do you even manage environment
variables in skills? I don't think
that's figured out yet. And there's less
risk of capabilities being missed. So if
you're totally overwhelmed LLM, yes, it
will still miss capabilities, but in
general, since everything is given up
front, there is no search and discovery
like with code execution or skills, and
so it'll miss things less. But then for
this side of the coin, we got the
flexibility here. So we can have dozens
of capabilities available to our agent
because we're not overwhelming with
context. We have our instructions for
how we reuse code or generate code and
the capabilities like the scripts that
we want to reuse loaded only when we
need it. And then also our agent can
also define workflows that are fit for
the task like combining different API
calls together. It's very flexible in
that way. So when you're thinking about
adding capabilities to your agents, I
want you to think about this trade-off.
But honestly, I think flexibility is
going to win over control more and more
over time because LLMs keep getting more
powerful. So, we trust them more with
code execution, searching, and
discovering capabilities. And AI agents
are meant to be autonomous after all.
So, we're just making them more
autonomous by upping the flexibility.
And so, that's everything that I have
for you here with the problem with MCP
and the solution with skills and code
execution. If you appreciated this video
and you're looking forward to more
things on AI agents and AI coding, I
would really appreciate a like and a
subscribe.